- [Anthony] When it comes to business software
that is used around the world by companies big and small,
nothing quite compares to the popularity
and reach of Microsoft Excel.
Excel is the most important and most used software
in business today, and mastery of it
is expected in most work places.
But managing Excel data can often be
tedious and repetitive.
This is where Python comes in.
Python is the fastest growing programming language,
and when you pair Python with Excel,
you unlock powerful tools that not only lighten
your workload, but also allow you to do more,
helping your team, or your company,
get to the next level.
My name is Anthony Sagely, and I'm passionate
about data science.
I teach Python and Excel, and I use these programs daily
to help businesses find efficiencies,
automate tasks, and ultimately, solve problems.
In this course, I'm going to show you how you can use
Python with Excel.
I'll show you how you can analyze large amounts of data
in Python that would be hard to manage in Excel,
how to import and work with reports,
as well as how to use both of these programs
to generate powerful data visualizations.
By the end of this course, you'll feel confident
to start using Python with Excel.
So, if you're ready to jump in, let's go.