- [Instructor] So what do you need to know to get the most
out of this course?
Well prior to this course, I expect you to have some
basic knowledge in Python and in programming.
This is a basic to intermediate course and we won't be going
over how to create variables or indent.
You should have Python installed.
Known syntax, and know other basics like loops
and conditionals.
Other than that, the only thing that's really required
is Excel.
I'll be running this on the Windows operating system,
I'll also be running our cord through Visual Studio Code
and its provided terminal, but you can run yours
through any text editor.
All of the files we'll be going over for examples will be
included with this course.