- [Instructor] When working with Excel,
there are many tools available
that allow interaction with Python.
One of the most popular tools is Pandas.
The Pandas library,
which is used primarily for data science,
makes it super easy for us to examine, sort,
or modify any data, even from Excel.
But how does it do that?
Pandas essentially creates a spreadsheet for us
in our Python code called the dataframe.
This dataframe has indexed rows and header columns
that both store what's called a series.
The series stores all the values in the rows and columns,
almost like the list.
Because both these objects are iterable,
Pandas makes it easy to traverse and pick up the data.
Using the dataframe,
we can do any kind of analysis or grouping we'd want
and export it to an Excel.
Before we jump in, let's get Panda set up
via the Pip installer in our command prompt.
For my system specifically,
I need to run pi dash M, pip install pandas.
As you can see, I already have it.
Now, let's open up Python in our terminal.
If we import Pandas and press Enter,
we see no errors and that means Pandas
was installed correctly.