- [Instructor] The first functions we're going
to go over in Pandas, are ways to get your data.
In Pandas, you can create a data frame from lists
or other objects in code.
Since we're using Python with Excel,
we're only going to look at how to create data frames
by reading files that already exist.
Now one tip I have before we get started,
is that I highly recommend following along
with the documentation that's provided by Pandas.
Many of the functions we'll be using have numerous flags
and multiple features to access that are outlined there,
and this tutorial will only use a few.
So the first thing we're going to do,
is head over to our text editor and import Pandas.
We do this by calling import Pandas as pd.
I'm also going to be importing a module of open pikes,
that I'll call the workbook, that will allow me to show you
saving to an Excel document.
Once we have these, we just need
to initialize our data frames, with the specified content.
The cool thing about Pandas is that
you can read multiple types of files.
This is handy because data can be structured
in any way and you'll still be able to interpret it.
So if we look at what we have in our working directory,
you'll notice that we have an Excel file,
a text file, and a CSV file.
Now all we have to do is create data frame variables
to specify for which kind of file we want.
So we'll have a data frame for our Excel file,
a data frame for our CSV file,
and a data frame for our text file.
Once we have those, all we have to do
is use the Pandas read function
to grab the data from the file.
So here, we'll have our Pandas.read Excel,
and at this point we're supposed to specify
the path variable, but because our files
are in our working directory, all we need is the name.
Now the same procedure follows for the other kinds of files.
And we'll specify for our CSV file,
and we'll specify the name, and for the text file,
we also use the read CSV function.
Now this is because there is essentially not too much
of a difference between a CSV file and a text file,
except for some little formatting differences.
So first, let's look at how Pandas formats our Excel file.
All we have to do is print this to console, and run it.
You'll notice that Pandas uses indices for rows
and headers for columns.
In our case, our indices are integers,
and our headers are strings,
such as region, unit, sales, and exports.
We'll be able to change this later,
but let's move onto the next one.
Now we'll print out our text file.
Now you'll notice here that Pandas
has a pretty handy feature where it'll abbreviate
all of your data, so it takes lines 0 to 4,
all the way down to 11,765, and that's pretty convenient,
but you'll also notice that the data
is formatted differently.
The indices are still present,
but the data's acting as a singular column.
This is because our word document is formatted in a way
that tabs separate each column.
Because of this, all we have to do is add a delimiter
to specify that we're looking to separate by tabs.
Now if we run this again, we should get
a nice formatted output,
and here we have our text file formatted
into three separate columns like it's supposed to be.
Now moving onto the CSV file.
Let's run that through terminal.
We can see that the indices are still intact,
but the first row of data is acting as a header
for the rest of the file.
In order to prevent this, we need to specify
that there is no header present in the CSV file.
So all we have to do is add a header flag, and specify none.
When we run this again, we can see that now the headers
are just integers.
So let's change this to something that's
a little bit more workable.
All we have to do is use the columns function.
So we have our df to CSV columns
and we set it equal to a list.
Now what do we want our columns to be?
So first here we have John Doe, and then an address,
a city, a state, and an area code.
So we'll just use those for our headers.
The first name, last name, address,
city, state, and area code.
So once we have that workable, we'll go ahead
and save this to our Excel file,
so we'll get rid of our print statement,
and we'll use our save function.
And then we get to choose a name for it and remember,
you always have to keep on your file extensions.
For our Excel, it's an xlsx file,
and we'll just call it modified.
If we run this, our file should appear
in our working directory.
Let's open this up and see that its formatted nicely
with our indices, our headers, and all of our data.
So there you have it.
As you can see Pandas is extremely useful
in working with data from different file types.