- [Instructor] When working with pandas,
manipulating the data frame is key
to getting what you want out of the data.
In this video, I'll go over some basic
selection and viewing functions,
as well as saving our desired values
to an Excel sheet.
Now the first thing we want to do
is have pandas and openpyxls set up.
So I'll go over to our text document
and import pandas as pd.
I'll also import the workbook module
from openpyxl.
(keystroke noises)
Once this is done, we need to have some data
stored into our data frame.
As a reminder, we are working with
the CSV file called Names
which I've already prepared the set-up for,
so I'll just paste that here.
Although we set up our own columns,
imagine if you had to deal with a spreadsheet
with so many columns that it was hard to fully
read the data through your terminal.
You need to know which columns contain what
so that you can access the data you need
to proceed.
In order to do this all we need to do
is use the same function
we used to assign the columns.
So let's print that here.
(keystroke noises)
And this will show us a breakdown and list format
for the data we're dealing with.
Now that we know how our data's
split up by column,
let's say you want to view just one column.
Panda's is a multi-row and multi-column
data structure, but it's functionality
makes it easy for us to do this in one line
with no iteration required.
All we have to do is index by the column name.
So let's say we want Last Name.
Then we just take the Last Name index,
and I'll clear this terminal for an easier view.
As you can see, this prints out all the values
in the Last Name column and their indices.
If you wanted to access multiple column's data,
we'd just pass it in as a list.
So let's say we want the State and the Area Code.
Then I'll clear my terminal
and I'll run it again.
Now you can see we have both the State
and the Area Code and their appropriate indices.
Now they only tricky thing to remember here
is that we use double brackets
because we're presenting the index
of the data frame as a list of columns.
Now if we had a large set of data,
we could only want to view
certain values in a column.
We can achieve this by slicing.
So let's say we want to take
the First Name column
and we only want the first three lines.
Let me clear my terminal and run this again.
As you can see this gives us
the First Name column,
but only the first three rows
and it's indexed from zero to two.
Now that we have some column viewing
functions down, we can deal with some
row functionality.
Because rows are indexed with integers
automatically by pandas,
we use these indices to locate them
specifically with the Integer Location function.
So let's use that real quick.
If we pass in the first index
and print that to terminal
then we should see that the row printed
corresponds to the index given at the i location.
The i location function is also
a very useful tool when iterating
though a data frame as you can increment
the row repeatedly.
Although pandas has some functionality
for more efficient ways of gathering data
rather than iteration,
we can also use the i location function
with two numbers or variables
and they correspond to a row-column value
or coordinate system.
But first let's print out our data frame
to see what we want.
Now let's say you wanted to get the name Repici,
the last name of John "Da Man" here.
We recognize that indices are numbered
starting at zero and our headers are strings.
However, when using the i location function
headers also correspond to integer values
for their length starting at zero.
So, if we wanted to return Repici
we would use the indices two and one.
So let's use our i location function here
and index two and one.
Now let's clear our terminal
and run this.
And there we have it.
Now on a final note, we can combine any of
these access and viewing functions for saving.
So if you consistently wanted to grab
certain rows or columns,
or even a specific location of an Excel file,
you can pick them out of your data frame,
store them, and save them.
So let's create a new variable
called our wanted_values
and let's say we wanted to take three columns
from our data frame.
Our First Name, Last Name and State.
If these were the only values
we wanted to extract from our data frame
then we could just save them to
an Excel document with our Save function.
(keystroke noises)
Now let's run this and check it out
in our working directory.
And now you can see we only get the First Name,
the Last Name and the State,
just like we wanted.
And there you have it!
Now you can manipulate and view any value
within a data frame of any size.