- [Instructor] A common problem for data scientists,
called the 80 20 problem, states that 80% of their time
is spent reading, cleaning, and reorganizing data.
Like in most samples of data, the larger the sample gets,
the more irregularities occur.
In this video, I'll be covering a few simple techniques
for organizing and cleaning our data.
So lets get started and import pandas.
We will also import numpy, or num pi.
This is included with pandas
and provides many different features.
But for now, we only need it to deal
with a nan or not a member values.
We'll also take the workbook module
from open py excel, so that we can save to our excel sheet.
So let's go ahead and set up the data frame
we've been using, I already have it prepared
and I'll paste it here.
The first step in cleaning our data
is getting rid of unnecessary columns.
In our case, we created these columns,
but imagine if we had numerous columns
and some didn't apply to anything we needed.
We can simply drop them.
First, we can create a variable called two drop.
But because we're only going to be dropping the addresses,
we can go straight to the drop function.
We can also pass on a list if we wanted
to drop more than one column,
but for now, we'll just drop addresses.
Notice that the drop function,
like most functions in pandas, has many flags.
The in place flag only confirms
that we are applying the changes to the data frame's
current instance just so we don't
have to write it equal to itself.
As you follow along in the documentation,
you should study up on what these flags can do for you.
Now, we drop the addresses, but we still want
to be able to identify where people live, specifically.
In this case, we should make our indexing by area codes.
Some people have the same area code
but in our case, they're unique.
It is more useful to use an identifier
that is unique for each object.
Imagine you had hundreds of thousands of library books,
each having their own identification number.
You could then search them and index
your data just by these IDs.
So let's set up our indexes for our area code.
Know that if we use the in place function
in our set index function, we wouldn't
have to set the data frame equal to itself.
So let's continue on and print
the location of our area codes.
This will return the row with the area code of 8074.
So let's run this.
As we expected, we get John Doe from Riverside, New Jersey.
However, we can still index rows with the indexes,
like an array with the I location function.
And we get the same exact row.
So, using an area code in a format like this
allows us to use these unique identifiers
to find people if we wanted to.
Now, for more cleaning purposes,
let's take a look at everyone's first name.
This is using a slice method.
Because there is no number on the right side of the colon,
it is taking the location of index 8074
to the end of the row.
Now, let's clear our terminal and run this.
Looking to the data, we see that some of the names
contain nicknames and quotes.
If you remember, when we searched for all Johns
who lived in Riverside, we only got one of the two.
So, we need to somehow read everyone's first name
and use a string function to split it by spaces.
In order to do this, we need to access
the first name column, call each object
to it's string value, and split it.
Let's run this and see what we get.
We can see that it splits every word
in the first column into it's own column.
Now all we have to do is somehow grab
the first column of the split.
However, pandas handles this for us pretty efficiently.
Now let's print this and see what we get.
We can see that the data frame only uses
the first column of the split as the first name.
Pretty easy, right?
The last thing we have to deal with
is the in addressable nan value.
All we have to do is locate the nan value of numpy
and replace it with a string that we can easily identify.
So, let's use the data frames replace function,
search for numpy's nan value,
and replace it with our own string.
Now, this should replace all nan values with the string, NA.
Lastly, let's save this to an excel
and check out our clean data.
Let's clear our terminal and run this.
Now we can head over to our working directory
and open up our new modified document.
As you can see, everyone has a single first name,
is indexed by their area code,
and all of the nan values are replaced by our NA strings.
And there you have it.
Our data set is now clean and easily addressable.