- If you've made it all the way to this video,
congrats on finishing the course.
Python supports an ever growing community of developers
and more tools are added constantly.
We covered the basics here, but there are always
more to learn, so here are a few basic resources
I recommend.
First, check out the documentation for both OpenPyxl,
and Pandas library, as they go very in depth
for all their functionality.
You can find them on their respective sites.
As you continue to build a base in Python,
and check out the opportunities that it offers,
check out the book called "Automate the Boring Stuff
with Python", by Al Sweigart.
In this book he covers the basics of Python
all the way to automating daily operations
that make your life easier.
And the book also features a chapter on Excel.
I encourage you to take your time and learn more
Python skills as it's a powerful tool
for your everyday troubles.
Good luck.