- [Instructor] If you've ever found yourself stuck
with the boring task of constantly reading over spreadsheets
for certain data,
copying and pasting to new Excel documents,
or just trying to make your data look good,
then Openpyxl is the library for you.
Openpyxl is a package in Python
that allows our code to interact
directly with Excel documents.
With Openpyxl,
we gain the freedom to manipulate
not just the data in the spreadsheet,
but the properties of the spreadsheet itself.
It does this by storing an Excel workbook
as well as the worksheets
as objects that we can alter with our code.
Openpyxl is the most used module
for dealing specifically with Excel,
as it allows us to do anything from styling sheets
to parsing data or creating graphs.
Before we get started,
we need to make sure that Openpyxl
is installed to our command prompt.
Running the pip install command,
we see that I already have it.
Next, let's open up our Python module.
When we import Openpyxl and press Enter,
if no errors appear,
then we've installed successfully.