- [Instructor] Because Excel is so widely used
across almost every industry.
There are many tools to choose from
when working with Python.
Openpyxl is a great all around choice
in that it supports functionality
for almost everything Excel.
So let's jump into our text editor
and get started with a small introduction to workbooks.
Let's import what we're working with in this video.
A workbook module, and a load workbook module.
Once we have that covered,
we can create the two most important objects
when working with openpyxl.
The workbook and worksheet.
We do this by using the workbook command.
We'll create a new variable, wb for workbook
and set it equal to workbook.
All this does is initialize a new workbook object
for us to work with.
Once we have that, we'll set up our worksheet.
So ws for worksheet equals workbook.active.
This just creates a worksheet reference
equal to the active sheet in our current workbook.
To make sense of what these represent,
let's hop on to an Excel document.
Now the workbook object is this all encompassing object
that we use to load and save,
and it contains the worksheets.
You can see the different sheets
down in the bottom-left corner.
Here we have Sheet1 and we can add a new one called Sheet2.
The worksheet is where we access all of our data,
our rows, columns or specific cells.
For now I'll show you how to create new worksheets
so let's head back to our Python document.
We can create new worksheets to add multiple pages
of data, we do this by calling the create sheet function
on our workbook object.
So we'll make two new sheets, worksheet one,
and worksheet two.
Then we just set them equal to our create sheet function
on workbook, and now we have to give it a name.
We'll just call this NewSheet.
We'll do the same process for the second worksheet.
And call this Another, but we'll add a zero at the end.
All this does is count as an index,
so in the order of our worksheets this one appears
before everything else.
Now on our workbook, we have two more worksheets
that we can work in between and add data to.
The next step is altering the title
of our current worksheet.
We can do this by using the title function.
Now that this is customized,
let's print out our sheet names property of the workbook.
And we'll run that through terminal.
As you can see our workbook contains three worksheets.
Each named how we added them, Another, MySheet and NewSheet.
Another sheet is first because of our index zero,
essentially we have just created two additional pages
to work with on Excel, one cool optimization tidbit
is that openpyxl won't actually create cells
on your worksheet as objects until they're accessed.
So creating and writing a new workbook like this
doesn't take too much memory.
Now let's look at loading an existing workbook
to access its cells.
All we have to do is use the load workbook function.
So I'll create a workbook variable
called workbook two and load in an existing Excel file.
I'll also add a new worksheet to this workbook
like we did for the last workbook,
but this time using the workbook two variable.
Now let's grab the active sheet of our workbook.
At this point we can start accessing cells,
in an Excel spreadsheet cell objects are indexed
by their column value which is typically A through Z
and their row value which starts at one.
Now if we remember our worksheet is the object
that contains all of the cell objects.
So if we want to grab the cell in the top left,
we know it should be cell A1
and we need to get it through our worksheet.
Openpyxl makes it easy to access this
by using the column and row name like an index.
So let's create a cell variable just to store it
and set it equal to our active sheet indexed at A1.
Now that we have our cell let's print it through terminal
and see what we get.
You'll notice that we're not printing any value
only the object notation.
We get a cell object in sheet one at the spot A1.
Now this is pretty handy because we can store cells
and objects and openpyxl has many properties of cells
that we can access, for now though we only want to focus
on the value inside the cell, so let's print that.
We see that region is printed, so the cell at A1
must contain a string value for region.
Now let's say we wanted to change the value
of that cell, we only need to index the location again
and set it equal to any value.
So we'll use A1 and set it equal to zero.
Now that that's done we'll save the workbook
with the simple save function and check it out.
Let's run this and navigate to our working directory
and open up this Excel sheet.
We can see that our A1 column has the value zero,
and now we can create our own workbooks, worksheets
and specific cells and modify them.