- [Instructor] When presenting large sets of data
to others, it is important to format it in such a way
that is readable and understandable.
If you want to create an Excel that's highly stylized,
appealing, and professional then openpyxl provides
the perfect formatting tools.
In this video I'll go over the basic merge
and unmerge functions as well as editing cell styles
and creating your own named style.
The first step to achieving a highly stylized spreadsheet,
is importing what you need.
Many of these style functions require their own import
and it's a lot to write, so I'll just paste it here.
We're also going to need to import
the basic workbook functions.
The next step is creating our workbook,
and getting our active worksheet.
Now just to show some styling options,
we're going to fill our spreadsheet
with some integer values.
We'll use a loop to do so.
Once we have that, we can access some cells to modify,
our basic merge functions are set up exactly
how you think they should be,
you just invoke your word sheet which holds all the cells
and call the merge cells function.
The same applies for the unmerge function.
Of course you need to specify the range of cells
you want to merge, let's use A1 to B5 as an example.
We simply pass in the slice to the merge functions.
You can also use these functions with a different notation
so that it's more easily accessible to merge with variables.
You simply pass in the start row and column,
as well as the end row and column.
If we wanted to merge from B2 to E5 our start row
would be two, our start column would be two
and our end row and end column would be five.
The one thing to remember about merged cells
is that they're addressed as their top-left cell.
So if I had all these cells merged from B2 to E5
I could save this entire merged cell into a variable
called cell by addressing the B2 position of the worksheet.
Now that we have this cell stored,
let's edit some of its style properties.
First let's change the font.
We won't mess with the type of font,
but let's change the color to red, make it a little bigger
and make it italics, we do this by changing
the cells font property.
Now that we know what the text is going to look like,
let's change the actual value.
Our newly merged cell contains the words merged cell
with the text being red, size being 20 and it's italics.
Next say we want our text to be in the bottom-right
corner of the cell, all we have to do
is change the alignment.
The alignment object takes two parameters.
The horizontal location and the vertical location.
Now let's make the background of the cell
a nice smooth transition from black to white.
To accomplish this we use the cell's fill property.
However we have to use one of the two fill functions
we imported, if we wanted a solid color fill
we could use pattern fill but in order to achieve
a nice transition let's use gradient fill.
For gradient fill we have to specify the color we stop at,
and the color we start at.
In openpyxl and Excel documents colors are encoded
in hexadecimal, in rrggbb format.
This means that the first two values correspond to red,
the second two to green, and the third two to blue.
Not let's say we wanted to start at black.
The hexadecimal encoding for this would be six zeroes
as none of the colors would have value.
Next we want to stop at white, the hexadecimal encoding
for this is six fs, this is because each red,
green, and blue color value are at their highest point.
Now that we've altered this merged cell,
let's save to the workbook.
Now we can quickly run this through our terminal.
Let's navigate to our working directory and check it out.
As you can see all of the changes we specified
are laid out, now it's definitely not the prettiest setup.
But in terms of creating templates and layouts for Excel.
Openpyxl can get the job done,
now let's head back to our Python script
and check out named styles.
Named styles are objects we can create
that store a style so that we can use it multiple times
instead of having to type all that out
like we did for our merged cell.
The first thing we do is initialize our style
we'll call it highlight.
We set this equal to a named style with the name highlight.
Now that this is initialized,
we need to change the properties,
first let's set the font to be bold.
Now in typical highlight fashion we need to darken
the borders and change the fill color.
To create thicker borders we need to create a variable
to hold the style of a side.
We'll make this side have a fixed style
and be black in color.
Once this is done we need to change
our named style's border property.
We do this by specifying for border
and setting each edge equal to our new style.
Now that the border is taken care of,
all we need to do is fill the cell with a solid yellow color
instead of using gradient fill,
we'll use pattern fill.
We'll set our red values and green values to as high
as they can be and have no blue value,
this will give us a nice yellow.
Now say we want to apply this style to every cell diagonally
starting at the H column.
First we need to make a count variable
and set that equal to zero.
Then we create a loop using our worksheet's
iter columns function, we'll set our minimum column
to eight for H and our minimum row to one.
We'll also set our maximums
so that it doesn't get out of hand.
Remember that in our iter cols function column
is stored as a list.
Because of that we can use our counter to index the list
for the rows we want, every time column moves over one
our counter should add one so we move one row down.
Now let's save this workbook,
and run this through terminal.
We can navigate over to our working directory
and check out our edits.
As you can see our highlighted style was applied
for all the cells we intended starting at H
and going only diagonal, now we can use these tools
to create stylized and professional spreadsheets.