- [Instructor] When creating an Excel document with Python,
it's always a good idea to add user functionality,
or just make the document look
more pleasing to the eye and professional.
In this video, I'll be going over openpyxl's features
to create a simple table, which is intractable
by the reader, as well as importing images.
One note before we get started is that,
image manipulation is not done solely through openpyxl,
and you may need to install a library
called Pillow via your pip installer.
Jumping in, the first thing we need to do
is import from openpyxl,
in our case, we need some table and image functions.
The next basic setup is to create
our workbook and worksheet.
Because I'll be loading in an Excel sheet
that we already created, we also need to import
our load_workbook function.
Now, we can continue on to loading in our workbook.
We also need to create our active worksheet.
Now let's open our Excel document
to see how our data is formatted.
We can see that our data is located from A1 to B5,
so let's keep this in mind as we create our table object.
We'll set up a variable called tab and set it equal
to a table object with the display name of Table1.
Next, we have to reference our data,
and we know our data is stored from A1 to B5.
Now that the table knows what it's called
and where to find the data,
it needs to know how to format itself.
From here, we use the table style information,
so let's create a style variable and set it equal
to the TableStyleInfo object.
Now we need to specify what's inside of the style,
we'll set the name to TableStyleMedium9.
We also need to tell it to show the first and last columns,
and whether to have row and column stripes.
Let's set the column values to False,
and then stripe values to True.
Once our style is done, we have all we need
to create a table, so we'll just set
the TableStyleInfo property to the style we just made.
For the last step, we need to
add the table to the worksheet.
Then we can save this as separate Excel document.
We'll just call it table.
So let's run this and head over to our working directory.
Now we can see that our data is formatted into a table,
the rows and columns are shaded and striped,
and the two header columns have this dropdown box
to make it reader intractable.
This is extremely helpful when creating tables
of large amounts of data because as you can see,
you can filter, sort, and select different values
within the table.
So, let's head back to our Python document
and talk about inserting images.
Again, you'll need the Pillow library
to insert images into your Excel document,
but it's a very handy library to have
because image manipulation can be done in just a few lines.
First, we want to have our image file
in our working directory,
if we don't, then we have to specify a path.
Next, we create an image variable,
we'll just call it img and set it equal to the Image object.
Now all we have to do is specify the image name.
Once that's done, we can simply add it to the worksheet.
Remember the cell we access is where
the top left of the image will be aligned,
so we'll set the picture so that it's
right next to our data, in cell C1.
Once the worksheet contains our image object,
all we need to do is save the workbook.
Pretty simple right?
Let's run this and go check it out.
Now we can see that our picture's saved
right next to our table, but let's say we were putting this
as a logo somewhere, and it was way too big.
The image object allows us to access
some of its properties, including width and height.
So, going back to our Python script,
before we add it to our worksheet, let's edit it,
all we need to do is set the width and height,
for example, if I wanted the image
to be a quarter of its current size,
then all we have to do is multiply its dimensions by 0.25,
so let's do that real quick,
utilizing the image's properties.
Once this is done, let's change our save file name
so that it doesn't overwrite our current image.
Now we can run this through terminal
and visit our working directory.
Our image is exactly a quarter of the size
of what it was previously,
now we can easily create better looking
and usable spreadsheets.