- [Instructor] When working with reports,
a graphical interface is important to keep in mind.
Openpyxl does not support features
to work with pivot tables
but we can format our reports to look nice
after we've analyzed the data and pandas.
In this video,
we'll go over some tricks to work with graphs and layouts.
So, let's import what we need to work with.
We'll be using a bar chart and a pie chart.
Now, we can load our workbook.
We'll use the template filled in with our crime csv data.
We also need to grab our active worksheet.
Now let's head over and look at our current report.
There are few things we want to take into consideration.
First, we'll notice that there's some thick borders
that format this area for us
and give us a set template for where our chart should go.
We want to create a chart
that will help us visualize the crimes
in each district by year.
For this, we'll use a bar chart.
Also note that we want our chart to be in the proper place
so we'll add it in the top left corner to cell B14.
Remember, that our data is accessed
from cell A8 to M13.
So let's go ahead and make a chart.
We'll create our data variable by referencing
cells A8 to M13.
Next, we just have to add our data to the chart.
Then, we'll add our chart to our worksheet at cell B14.
Finally, we'll save this and run our code.
So let's go check it out.
Now we can see that our graph
is not looking exactly how we wanted.
First of all, there's no title
also the key is by district rather than year
which makes way too many bars to look over
especially if we wanted to identify a single district.
In addition, there's an entire extra
and empty section of the chart.
We need to fix all these chart formatting problems
as well as resize the chart to cover
the area we want it to.
But first, let's see how Excel
would recommend making the chart.
So let's delete our current chart,
highlight all of our data,
head over to insert,
recommended charts and open the first one.
We can see that this chart is much cleaner
and closer to our objective.
The districts are laid out cleanly
and the years are the bars.
However, we do have an extra year value
in the key that we'd want to get rid of.
So, just for learning sake,
let's see how Excel set this up.
The data ranges from cell A8 through M13
but that's how we had it set up last time.
So if we go to edit
you'll notice that the series name is year
at the year cell A9
and the series values are empty from B9 to M9.
So we know that this is coming from rows instead of columns.
Next, let's edit the districts.
We can see that it calls them access labels
so we just need to add them as labels.
Let's make the edits for our graphs.
We'll make the data variable have the minimum row 10
so that we exclude just the year
and then take in the rest in the values of the districts.
Then, we'll make a labels variable.
Then, we'll make a labels variable
to reference all the districts
so they're not in the data set.
Now we have to make sure that when we add the data
we specify that it's taking from rows
just like we saw in the recommended graph.
Other than that, we'll add a title
and make sure to include the labels.
The last part is figuring out the height.
We can do some math to figure this out
but we don't know the default values of the graph.
So let's set them both equal to 10.
Let's run this and go look at our current graph.
We can see that the graph is almost six cells wide.
Dividing 10, the graph's current width,
by six we get 1.6.
Now we want our graph to be a total of 12 cells wide
so we multiply these to get 20.
However, it was not exactly six cells
so we need to add a little bit.
Let's call it 20.3.
We can do the same process with the height
and we get 4.56.
Now we'll add a pie chart.
This pie chart will represent our totals columns.
Our labels were in O7 to P7
with our data in O8 to P8.
We have to take these from rows
just like in the previous bar chart
but the process is still the same.
Now let's add the data and set the categories.
And then create the title.
Finally, we need to set the width and the height.
Now because both charts
are between the same horizontal lines,
the height is the same.
Next, if we do the same math steps
we find that the width is 8.45.
Now, we'll add the chart to the worksheet.
Now, we can save this and run it one last time.
And there you have it.
We have a nicely formatted report
with graphs and data in our templates.